[Music]
i'm fredo holds and i welcome you to the
perspectives podcast with my today's
guest
daniel schmuckenberger he has done work
in functional medicine
and biotech in education and in human
development and advise
private and public sector leaders on how
to address
complex scenarios across a number of
fields
his central interest is long-term
civilization design
and i'm super excited to hear more about
his perspectives
hey everyone i'm really excited to
launch my first episode of my first ever
podcast
and i couldn't be happier to have um my
guest today with
who is daniel schmuttenberger
um very easy for me to say his name
because uh
it's a german version probably more
difficult for americans
i'm actually very excited um that
you're my first guest daniel because i
remember our first encounter in san
diego
one and a half years ago we just talked
about it and
this was one of the most inspiring
conversations that i've had in the last
years
and it was mostly because of your
different way to to think about the
world and the things that you care about
and that you're driven by
to change in this world and so i'm
really excited to
explore more of your perspective today
and be able to pick your brain
and and hopefully um share um
some some value with with other people
in in the audience
so thanks for being with us it's an
honor to get to
be on your first podcast
so actually i want to start um in right
away
with um we already
mapped out some topics or the most
interesting topics and one thing that
immediately stood out to me was
the topic of perspectives and
perspective seeking
so um danny i have a very
uh personal question as well like
what's your what's your perspective
seeking approach like how do you come
to believe what you're believing right
now
well the reason that this came up as we
were starting to dialogue was you said
that you were thinking of calling the
podcast perspectives
it feels valuable since that's a deep
central theme to what you want to do
here to actually explore that topic
itself
so if you don't mind me switching roles
for a minute
why did you want to do a podcast on
perspectives oh
i love that um so
personally because i just go by i just
go by feeling
and i remember this feeling very
distinctively i've talked oftentimes i
shared your content oftentimes with
with people your podcast uh on forward
thinkers is probably one of the podcasts
i shared the most
uh in the past and um
this i i get this trickling feeling of
excitement when i hear
something that i feel is is is growing
me is is challenging me is expanding my
perspective because it's changing my
experience how
how i interact with my environment and
i feel it in a way where i feel more
positive about the way
i i engage with my environment and
that's why i'm so excited to
to hear different perspectives and also
in that process i'm learning with every
new perspective that i
that i that i hear that i experience i
realize
something that um is i think that
i consider the path my personal path of
consciousness
is i'm realizing that i'm
it's not only me my perspective is not
the only relevant one
is not the only right one and the more i
experience that i feel the
the healthier i live the happier i
am and so that that's why i care so much
about perspectives and exploring
perspectives
yeah well the fact that you say you feel
happier is you're exposed to more
perspectives even if they're ones that
might
uh invalidate previous views you had or
at least show the inadequacy of them
is a really healthy psychological
orientation
because if every time you realize that
your previous best understanding of the
world was really inadequate you feel
badly
then it will end up
having you want to do confirmation bias
and look for things that confirm what
you currently think and
that's going to limit the scope of
obviously what you can understand about
reality and how effective you can be
in acting on it so there's kind of a
there's an epistemic drive right
epistemology meaning how do we go about
knowing stuff there's an epistemic drive
that can have its own incentive where
there is a like you mentioned like a
joy or an aliveness just from coming to
understand something better
and when that becomes stronger than
whatever kind of
fragile identity structure wants to be
seen as already having it figured out
then the rate of learning obviously goes
up quite a lot and
so i'm happy for us to start by
exploring the topic of perspective
because we would be
whatever other topic we were exploring
we'd be exploring it through
perspectives
um so it's valuable to look at the
process by which we look right
perspective even though
the word is from optical science is
looking at the world and the key
kind of insight the first insight is
that
when i'm looking at something and i have
a perspective on it
it's not what what i'm seeing is not
actually the thing
because if i went to the other side i
would see something else and if i zoomed
in with a microscope or if i looked in
the ultraviolet spectrum or with a radio
telescope or i would see something else
right
so i'm getting a perspective i'm getting
some bandwidth of light bouncing off of
one side of something
with some error or whatever coming in a
certain resolution into my eyes
and so one very valuable insight is
that perspective
in the process of perceiving something
inherently reduces the total information
of the thing
so my perspective on something is never
actually the thing
right and i need many i need to take
many many different perspectives to even
start to get a sense
so of course if i'm looking at a
building from the west side or the east
side or the north side or from an aerial
view or inside one room or inside
another room
they're all true and they're all partial
and if i tried to hold it as if well
which one is it that would make no sense
because it's not a 2d object right it's
this very complex 3d object with
internal structure and
so they're all true they're all partial
and but if i'm trying to collapse
a complex 3d thing to 2d right to a
single perspective that i can take a
picture of it's just going to be wrong
it'll have some truth value in it but to
the degree that i think it's adequate
it'll be
it'll be a whole dimension wrong which
is infinitely wrong right there's a
whole
infinity of another dimension missing
and
we do this with our perspective on
social topics or
other people or the nature of reality
all the time
and so then even if i take
all of the pictures and i say okay i'm
going to take as many pictures as i can
and of course i can never
show that i took every perspective on it
i
maybe i didn't get under the table and
have a look at what maybe a kid sees
in their view of the house their main
memory might be that view from under the
table when they think of the house right
or uh whatever i miss the aerial view
so that's one thing is that you can
never show
closure over the perspective space i
won't say never for the most part in
reality you can never show closure over
the perspective
and then even if i take a lot of the
pictures it's pretty good
representation i put them in as a
collage in 2d that's still not what the
house looks like
because it's still not 2d so then i
could sew them together into a video and
i take a video tour of the house right
well i still don't see the whole thing
at once
but i added another dimension back in
that which is time
right the video is showing over time so
i have i have 2d and then i have the
connection of all these 2d images
through the flow of time and now i'm
back at the right kind of dimensionality
and so i can get a sense of more
adequate kind of sense of
so when i was fairly
young i noticed that when people were
arguing
about political topics or philosophic
topics
um that there was usually a dialectical
kind of thing going on where there was
some truth value
and some inadequacy to explain all of
the other truth values but they were
they were seeing the west side of the
house or the east side and be
they were over emphasizing the part that
felt most real and meaningful to them
based on the perspective of the reality
they had
and and so how to be able to seek
to see through the other perspectives
and then speak
higher not higher perspective because
you don't get your perspective right how
do you seek a higher
trans perspective synthesis
um this is something that like this is
philosophy 101 right this is the
the hegelian dialectic what is it take a
particular view on something
and postulate it you have a thesis and
then find something that seems like
almost the exact opposite view but that
some people believe in and you have an
antithesis
those will usually be at a similar level
of complexity right similar number
if i if i tried to express the view
under maximum information compression
it'd be similar-ish
um and so this can look like
the debates that you see around
capitalism and communism
or similarly around uh the democratic or
republican or generally left or right
kind of political platforms
which can often be thought of as having
to do with more emphasis
on the collective and the whole or more
emphasis on the individual
right rights and responsibilities
various things like that
but they actually don't it's not that
there is kind of a
a gradient with zero and negative and
positive numbers and you find the right
place between rights and
responsibilities
it's that there's actually perpendicular
axes
and that you can increase rights and
responsibilities at the same
time but it's in a higher dimensional
space right you kind of have to get that
higher dimensionality right otherwise
people
will default to thinking the thing that
they really care about
is being automatically threatened right
their perspective also encodes a value
there is something that they value
within that thing
that perspective and then they might
kind of vehemently oppose or not want to
hear another perspective because it
seems like if
that one is held as true it's this one
is true or that one is true and if that
one's held as true
then it will invalidate the value here
as opposed to the synthesis
is actually a higher order of complexity
you under maximum compression of the
good statement of it there would be more
total bits required
and it'll end up including the true
parts of each of these and
how they relate what the nature of the
feedback cycles
for the higher perspective so thesis
antithesis
synthesis but the synthesis is not of
the same type
right it is a includes and transcends
type function
now i must say there's a lot of people
who hate hegelian dialectics
because particularly there's a lot of
kind of uh
empirically or poparian oriented people
because a dialectic has been abused
as a tool for manipulation
uh but it's like every tool can be
weaponized
right so the fact that i can beat
somebody to death with a hammer doesn't
mean a hammer has no legitimate purpose
and that we should
always be where we run with hammers it
means
pick any tool in my house and i could
make a weapon out of it if you want it
right and similarly pick any
intellectual tool and i can make a
weapon out of it i can use
the principles of critical thinking as a
way to just be an asshole and tell
everyone that they're in logical fallacy
all the time
um so hegelian dialectic has been
weaponized to say okay
what is the conclusion i want the other
person to come to whether it's true or
not for my own game theoretic purposes
i'll phrase that as a synthesis and then
i will reverse engineer a thesis and an
antithesis both of which will have
little
errors hidden but all use principles of
rhetoric
and i'll frame it up that there's some
truth here there's some truth here and
the synthesis is obviously true
so that weapon has been used all the
time but that doesn't
tool is not actually valid so i it has
to do with what is the intent and the
capacity of the use of the intellectual
tool
now the last part there is it's not
always
thesis and antithesis there might be
lots of different perspectives
right there might be lots of different
insights around a thing going on and how
do we
factor all of those to be able to inform
both our understanding of the world and
where we have collective choice making
to engage in
because whether we build a utility or a
road isn't an individual
choice only it's like those are things
that we engage in and so
whether we do that through a democratic
process or a meritocratic process or
whatever
all of our social systems are systems
for how do we collectively figure out
how to
coordinate things bigger than
individuals can do on their own
and that does involve coordinating how
we're sense making the world
and coordinating what we think is
valuable and
my ability to actually
perceive what is valuable to you and
what you how you're making sense of the
world
without it seeming like a threat to my
own
and then be able to see are there higher
order frames
they can take what you value and what i
value and what you're seeing is true
what i'm saying is true
correct the distortions either of us
have
and be able to offer better insights
forward
than have been there previously i i
really like i really like that take um
and specifically two things uh that i'd
like to summarize that stood out to me
is i think on the first
the first statement that every
perspective
has truth in some in some part
and the second that
the partiality of it that it's always
just
true um
[Music]
as a part of a bigger picture or it's
one one
one truth that is a part of a bigger
picture and i think this
this um the more we try to force
uh or or reduce this partiality and say
like okay no my truth is the only truth
or
or is the is the the the biggest part
the the most relevant part
and and reduce the dimensionality and
say okay it's like
it can only be my truth or your truth um
i think then
that that's um a good over
a good transition to talk about sense
making right because
um once we've established that it's like
hey every perspective has
truth right and um
it's a part of a bigger picture now it's
about
what you said in your last sentence is
okay wait a second how can we
make more sense of that because if all
perspectives are relevant
we need to understand all these
perspectives and we need to listen
and we need to find consensus to make
sure that we can
proceed and progress and and
develop into a higher higher stage
of human consciousness as well or or
consensus
so what's your take on on sense making
um the status we are in right now as a
society
on a global level and and what do you
see as the
most relevant parts right now to to
focus on
big topic
so there's some tools we need to
construct together first
so when we're talking about the
partiality
or the um believe completeness of a
view there's a very deep topic that
comes up which is a
person's relationship with the known
the unknown and the unknowable
and because a lot of people who
have the sense that their view is pretty
complete
don't have a very deep relationship with
the unknowable
and with the extent of the category that
is the
unknown unknowns right and
so they don't realize that
everything they know is can be
represented in a
finite number of bits and usually a
relatively small finite number of bits
and the totality of reality
via tarsky's theorem or girdle's theorem
or whatever is fundamentally infinite
and so they know no fraction right
mathematically represented fraction
and so um you know nothing basically
as a fraction of all that is
and um
and so this leads to certainty bias and
this is one of the things i became
rubios of
early because as someone who is very
interested in learning
when i was pretty young i would learn
things and get excited and then i
realized that
i knew more about a topic than some
people around me and then i get over
certain that i understood the topic
and then i would learn more and i'd be
like oh there's like whole
universes around this i didn't even know
i was unaware of
right like when people start learning
math and the most advanced thing they've
ever heard about when they're a kid is
calculus
they don't know the whole universe or
beyond calculus that they aren't
factoring so
by the time they're in eighth grade they
think they're getting pretty close to
knowing all of math
right and and that's the case in
most any field including understanding
reality which includes new fields all
the time
and so one of the things happened for me
was i
started getting really embarrassed
about the things that i had been sure
about that then i became completely
clear were wrong
and not wanting to do that thing a bunch
right and that started to temper
the relationship to premature certainty
and um
and then i found it very interesting to
study history
and look at how many things that humans
believed so fervently that they would
die in war
for the belief where they would kill
other humans for the belief that all
seem ludicrous to us now like pretty
much all of it
and how easy it is for us to see
where previous people were wrong about
what they were certain of they had the
genetically same brains as us
and how easy it is for us to
sense that someone else is completely
wrong about something that
they're very deeply certain of but that
nobody can actually think of a single
belief that they currently hold that
they think they're wrong about
and yet they're probably wrong about
almost everything
and that's a really disastrous human
condition
because those wrong beliefs inform
action
and so if i'm continuously navigating on
a map that's not true i'll be driving
into cliffs and
right like it's important that i
calibrate my map
especially as i want to do more
significant action for most people it
doesn't matter that much because the
scope of what they're trying to do
allows their ignorance to not be hitting
them in the face all the time
now it's very easy to overcompensate in
the other direction
and to say okay anytime that anyone has
ever been certain
it was unwarranted and there are
actually
no absolute truths therefore there's no
even relative higher truth claim
everything is just perspective
and anyone who claims that something has
more validity
is somewhere between immature and an
imperialist
and that's kind of the direction that a
lot of the postmodern
movement of thinking went right but this
is also gibberish
because we will be acting in the world
and we'll be acting on some information
and it's not equally good information
and some things make rocket ships work
and some things don't make rocket ships
work
and we can be pretty empirically clear
about whether
a technology works based on our
understanding of it or not
and if if we have to treat a viral
condition or make decisions regarding
policy or whatever it actually really
matters that we are getting
things right regarding this right and so
this is
what we've tried to develop things like
the scientific method and
the various domains of science and those
types of epistemic tools for
but we also start to get quickly into
the place that the way we
think about science formally is
a method that can be applied to the
domain of things that are both
measurable and repeatable
well there are things that are real that
are not measurable like every experience
you've ever had
i can measure what's happening in your
brain in some very narrow dimension
it's pretty hard to do an fmri and a qeg
and whatever on you at the same time
because they
are affecting each other and all of that
still only gives me a tiny bit of the
total
insight right but i can't measure your
experience
i can't do a third person process on
first person
and there's also lots of real stuff that
is measurable but not repeatable
like all novel phenomena and so then i
can try and do statistics and but then
that's not quite science
right so we start to realize that
science is necessary but not sufficient
to understand the nature of reality
so then the question is what
what are the right methods what are the
right epistemics to go about
coming up with the confidence margin
what confidence do i need to inform what
kind of action based on how
consequential the action is
and based on how consequential
non-acting is
and so this is now getting us into
sense making but i can't sense make well
if i have a bias towards wanting more
certainty than i really have the right
foundation for or i have a bias towards
being uncomfortable with any certainty
and wanting to
continue to dwell within uncertainty and
multi-perspective
process without actually integrating
them and so
this is an interesting place where like
emotional biases and existential and
identity biases end up affecting
cognitive biases
and uh and yet perspective taking is
connected to all of it which is why i
really like the name of the podcast and
why i thought it's in
the topic is
when i'm doing repeatability in science
that's actually a perspective process
i'm wanting to make sure
that this particular thing that i'm
holding as objective is true across all
of these perspectives that hold the same
context
right that it's not subjective or
intersubjective the subjective
obviously that doesn't science doesn't
give me how to do governance because
governance has a lot of first person and
second person stuff
right like mostly all of it but it's
informed by third person so
there i have to do perspective seeking
of like what
it's so easy like in the us right now
especially politically it's so easy to
take a whole group of people on the
other side of the political spectrum and
just throw them all out as bad and dumb
and both sides do it kind of equally
well
and without
even being able to empathize with why
they seem bad and dumb to the other side
or why the other side could actually see
anything that way
now when you ask what are the source of
the problems this is one of the source
of the problems
and this creates radically inefficient
government this creates war
this creates poor coordination and poor
shared sense making this creates
super inefficiently utilized resource
it's also why the divorce rate is so
high and why people have shitty
relationships
at the micro level when i used to do
relationship counseling with people
one of the things which is everyone
should
be a relationship counselor for a little
while in your life because
when you watch other people doing it is
so obvious and so dreadful and then you
realize that you did that and then
you're ashamed to ever do that again and
it helps
but typically this pattern that i would
see again and again was that
the couple would sit down and in
her version of the story
it's so clear how things would be better
if he did stuff differently
she's tried all the things that she can
try
and she can't make it better um which is
why she's frustrated she's there
because obviously he has to and in his
version of the story things would be
better if she did stuff differently
and this is why they're on their path to
divorce
and all that can do because they're not
perspective taking
right so i started all that can do is
make them resent each other and feel
powerless
and then to the extent that they feel
powerless and the other person has to
change
trying to control the other person is
the best thing they could possibly do
and uh and this is actually another
important point when you wanted to start
coming
back to the world is if if we can't
sense make even what the experience of
the people closest to us
is and can't resolve those conflicts
we're so not qualified to be able to
help israel and palestine or the us and
china or
like it's important to realize that
that's those personal experiences are a
training ground to get very basic
capacities because the larger issues are
still just human issues
multiplied by a lot of scale um
and so one of the things i started doing
was to just speed it up because i was
tired of the process where
she would tell her side of the story and
he'd be shaking his head the whole time
and
she and he still wouldn't get it and
then he'd tell his side of the story and
she'd be crying feeling so unseen and
misunderstood and whatever
and so i just stopped them in the
beginning and be like look i know you
both know your own side of the story so
i don't want you to tell it to me
i want you to tell the other person side
of the story from the beginning right so
husband tell me
why she's upset what she perceives what
she would like to be different
before you do i want you to tell me how
good you think you're going to do with
this
like how well do you think you probably
understand it and then i do the same
thing
and what was interesting was they never
did a good job
if they did they wouldn't have those
problems but they always thought they
would do a better job than they did
so not only did they do a bad job
of understanding each other but they
didn't even realize how badly they
didn't understand each other right
because it was an unknown unknown class
that they weren't even recognizing
but i think it all comes down to the
topic of certainty then um
where it's like how certain i am in what
i
believe to be true and how open and then
at the other side how open am i to
look at things that are outside of what
i believe to be true
and to change what i believe to be true
with it certainty is an important part
which is why i brought it up
one can have certainty that what i think
has some
value without having certainty that it's
close to complete
and this is why it's so important to
recognize the unknown unknown class not
just the that i know that i'm
unaware of
but that that there might be that i
am not even imagining that changes my
sense making completely
but the the most difficult part i
struggle with is
okay what you mentioned before is
i i perceive humans to be mostly
relative thinkers it's like okay i have
this thing that i compare myself or my
view or my
my idea to and so now okay i'm looking
at the unknown i'm looking at all the
potential things that
are could be there will be there um
and now as you said before it feels
infinite
and how do i compare my
limited or like yeah my limited
understanding to
something that i that is infinitely hard
to understand for me
like this this part i i con constantly
struggle with him when you said like
okay
sense making a part of that is certainty
like how do i ever
can say it's like oh i'm that and this
certain about this and this pers
like this and this viewpoint or this and
this action like how do you approach
that
yeah so this is great because you just
entered the domain of
religion which is um
what types of certainty can we have or
not in the domain of what we would call
the infinite or
total reality or something like that and
um
and you can see with regard to the
certainty bias
there's a lot of people who feel
absolutely certain that they know the
nature
of ultimate reality all the way to how
the universe was created and
where how it will end and what god's
name is
[Laughter]
you're that certain about all that
um
and then you see another
what i would say is a more mature
relationship to that same impulse
which the mystics in all of the
religions talked about the great
unknowable but that
they can have some sensed relationship
with
and um so the first verse of the tao te
ching
you think about this like okay so lao
tzu is going to take all of his wisdom
write it down in this set of verses the
very first verse says
the dao that is knowable is not the
eternal dao
right what's your interpretation of that
well the knowables finite
and so it is the knowledge that's
knowable is not the eternal knowledge
the dow that is nameable
that is finite is not the whole thing so
then the nameable the finitely
describable is the beginning of the
great confusion
right so a lot of people
reflect on that and they get that okay
so i'm never gonna actually have
complete understanding of ultimate
reality
but then the next part to get is that he
still then went on to do a bunch more
verses wrote a whole book of words
that were not useless right which is
don't think that you have absolute
certainty of the whole but don't think
that it's not worth gaining
relatively increased insight also
but nevertheless it's difficult to
[Music]
um i don't feel like we start at that
point of we know nothing
and we can relatively increase our
knowledge
i feel it's more like we we feel like we
know
40 percent and with every experience we
decrease that percentage by realizing oh
actually maybe i didn't know that much
so i i feel these are two different uh
yeah they're little experiences this is
that dunning-kruger curve right
and um
and so there's this beautiful process
that as we go on learning more in life
we both
know actually more and have
less total certainty and recognize
what a tinier percentage it is and those
people are ultimately more trustworthy
um and more curious
and more open-minded probably and more
empathic
and i mean i i find it interesting
because when i look at that i feel
all these subparts that we can look at
is like
oh i want to listen i want to be a good
listener i want to be trustworthy honest
like all these things
are kind of results of that that process
at least that's how it seems to me
so this this was an interesting thing i
was
thinking about a moment ago um
so in the field of developmental
psychology where you're looking at like
piaget's work and on how children
develop through different discrete
stages where they don't have language
and then they do and they don't have
abstract reasoning
there's no reason to think that the
development of human capacity stops
around
18 or puberty or whatever that's it
what are the higher stages that humans
can continue to go to
is this whole very interesting field of
psychology developmental
psych and it kind of is also what all of
the
religions and philosophical and
self-development traditions focused on
which is what does
the what does the development of a human
being what are the upper bounds of its
potential
what is actually a meaningful human life
and and what are the practices and
processes to get there
and whether you're looking at like the
ethical line of development someone
increasing their kind of ethical
awareness nuance capacity or their
cognitive
or their domain understanding or their
interpersonal or their whatever
[Music]
in the literature on developmental psych
all of the higher stages of development
of any of those lines
had a lot of correspondence with
perspective taking that as people were
able to take more perspectives they did
better
in terms of higher stages of especially
interpersonal
um and complex type things there's a
colleague in the integral world and his
name is clint
fuse and he did a dissertation that he
was telling me about a few years ago
that i found very interesting because he
was looking at all this literature
deeply on higher stage of human
development what you might call
growth in consciousness or enlightenment
or abstract kind of terms like that
and looking for what things seem to
statistically correlate the most across
the literature and he found the slight
refinement which was that it wasn't
perspective
taking as a capacity it was perspective
seeking as an orientation
that was kind of the generator function
of the development the development was
arising from an
impulse to seek more perspectives
whereas someone might have the capacity
to do it but not actually
do it very much because there isn't the
innate kind of seeking and so
how to actually notice that impulse in
you and how to deepen it and then also
notice what makes you turn it off and
double down
on your own perspective and work with
that will end up being a generator
function of
taking a lot more perspectives which
means seeing a lot more of the world
right as i see the world through a lot
more lens i get a lot more
insight because
something i saw as a kid was i was like
i would see this
i would see a mechanical engineer
looking at the world and realizing he
was seeing a totally different world
than i was seeing
he was looking like everywhere he was
looking was how stuff was designed and
how what types of screws and levers and
the mechanics and the and
then like a hair stylist was seeing a
totally different world seeing i
never paid attention to and a physicist
and a chemist and a biologist and i'm
like
i'm not seeing the world i'm seeing what
my relevance filter showed me is
relevant that i even know to
look for and i didn't see the
the types of screws and levers on
everything before but now that i do that
the whole world don't
have any insights about everything
perspective seeking right
but it's also growth in
cognitive insights it's also increased
humility for sure recognizing holy
that
i just was missing universes um
and still am and then it's also the
ability to do much better leadership and
governance because
i know that the other people aren't
seeing the same world and yet their
worlds
are valuable and i think that last part
is
the most important part is that their
view is valuable
in that that i think is a
very relevant topic also now applying
that more to
to the actual real-world situation we're
in right now
um how can we apply this thought process
more
to the world we live in right now how
can we establish
uh systems that that
like involve more of that sense making
that deeper sense making but also that
developing into higher stages of
consciousness how
what's your take on that
so
let's say that i'm listening to try to
hear the signal in someone as opposed to
instantly negatively react to the noise
or what i perceive to be the noise
first what that thing i just said will
fix your relationships more than almost
anything else
which is if when your partner or your
family member or friend is
saying something if you're listening to
try to actually hear what's true
in their experience first and then
where you would refine or add or
disagree later
like everything will go better
and because they think it's true and if
you relationship is
can we actually relate um
and if i'm just going into where they're
wrong i'm not relating which is why
the nature of my response then will
break the relationship
[Music]
now if i'm listening for what's true and
what someone's saying that doesn't mean
that what they're saying
isn't also flawed and maybe even
catastrophically flawed
but i'll at least understand how to
relate with it better
right so if we look at
you were mentioning you know we're in
the middle of this kind of covid
global pandemic and then the systemic
fragility we were already in before that
and the
fractured information ecology and
political divides and
tribalism and whatever and then how
those things have been
playing out and getting worse under this
pressure
so let's say you take a topic like
that's very divisive like conspiracy
theories
and typically the moment the topic comes
up people have already made up their
mind and instantly cleaved
like they don't need to hear anymore
they're like this tinfoil hat wearing
is a danger to society
how do we shut them up and have them not
kill everyone with the plague
um and
or someone just starts to hear about
conspiracy and they're like yeah i
probably will believe this
i'm probably interested in this whoever
talks about this are probably my people
right and what's interesting is there's
like an intuitive resonance like that
and it doesn't mean every conspiracy
theorist agrees with every
thing that any particular person says
but
so as i over generalize to just kind of
make a point and then we can add the
nuance back you can see that there's
that's a very strongly polarizing thing
where then there is basically no
perspective seeking across that divide
usually that happens
well if you
ask in abstract
so asking an abstract is helpful because
we'll remove all the emotional tension
of this situation
so conspiracies have have some people
shared information with some other
people to coordinate for some activity
that they don't
share widely with everyone for their own
personal gain throughout history
is that a thing that happens yeah of
course that's a thing that
happens happens
all the time it's the it's all of what
you can call like political strategy
and so then do some people get very good
at intentionally lying and misinforming
you were a poker player right a bluff is
is it
done that before yeah and so
we were intentionally mastering the art
of misinformation disinformation for a
game theoretic advantage right
and soccer player does it when they fake
to go this way and then they actually go
this way or they're like
in any game theoretic scenario truth
about reality equals adapt
equals competitive advantage so you want
to throw the other guy off
so if i'm a politician or if i'm running
a business and trying to corner the
market or whatever it is i'll try to
create both withhold my true information
and
create some false information so i can
advance so depending on
depending on the goal of the
the defined goal right if your goal is
your personal events
then maybe yes but if your goal is to
actually make the
society father like flourish then
theoretic scenario we're not talking
about a coordination game right but a
zero-sum type game yeah so then
truth becomes one of the weapons it
becomes one of the things that we fight
the battle with
um so withholding information trade
secrets patents classified information
and then disinforming
right propaganda whatever
well you don't have to study history
very much to see that you can see the
entire lens of the history of the world
through that lens and it's a very
insightful lens and
and sun tzu was talking thousands of
years ago about how to conspire
effectively
right and how to break conspiracies
effectively and machiavelli was talking
about it and so
the idea that that's not a thing is just
silly
that said lots of the conspiracy
theories that
said such and such was going to happen
by this date never happen
and so they're like objectively clearly
wrong
and so to kind of generally bias towards
or away from that as a whole class is
silly
you can't think of it as a class in that
way
um so but let's just say that we do
and we or we're looking at the people
who do
so there's a
i've never actually seen an information
ecology and news ecology
more up than i'm seeing right now
with regard to kobe because
you've got like it's not even just the
popular news it's even science journals
right it's
the uk saying oh we're going to stay
open and do herd immunity and then like
a couple days later oh
actually everyone's gonna die because
the imperial college just said this
thing and
so we're actually gonna lock down for 18
months and then oh no
we over-corrected and that we're gonna
and so
um the the range
even of within the scientific literature
of ideas and guesses about it
is orders of magnitude of and
partly that's because it's a novel virus
and
partly it's because things like
epidemiology are actually complex
and this one where you have a long
contagious asymptomatic period is
particularly complex to try to forecast
like the unknown unknowns are quite high
so similarly any one who has a
kind of sense in them of mistrust of the
state
and state type authorities and they
think that any state action that is
going to decrease their freedom is
probably some
deep state conspiratorial cabal that is
trying to
uh remove everyone's freedoms and
oppress them
they're going to just automatically tend
to
react to certain news in their news feed
more than others
right this is where the confirmation
bias thing comes in and
since most people when they read
news they aren't reading science
journals they're reading news that maybe
discusses something
in science and they don't go check the
science journal themselves they decide
at a feeling level this feels true they
don't even realize they're doing it
right because they didn't go through and
look at the science journal look at all
the journals on the topic find the
experts who disagree find why they
disagree look at the methodology and see
is
is the conclusion epistemically grounded
there's like see i knew the thing wasn't
real or c i knew it was going to kill
everyone
where really it's just hitting a
predisposition that's resonant and then
they're going with that resonance
and
but it goes in both ways right so there
are
the other side that just generally tends
to think
that there is this thing called
legitimate authority and legitimate
experts and that science is real and
science has the answers and it
and that there are these things called
science deniers and they might be
anti-climate changes or anti-vaxxers or
whatever and they're all dangerous and
they're all problems and we just need to
like trust the scientific authorities
and
they'll tell us what to do and
that's also kind of like a like an
emotional disposition
more than it is a very well analyzed
position
right and they're both silly
they both have a little bit of truth too
and they're both silly right
and it's important to see the truth
because otherwise
you won't understand a lot of why the
world thinks what it is and you won't be
able to be effective if you don't
understand
why people think what they think um
and you'll also be getting it wrong if
you don't understand the partial truth
so if i
if i'm to say okay
there's a group of people for whom if
anything comes from a major
uh authoritative scientific institution
they assume it's part of the great
conspiracy
um and it's the standard model bias and
uh whatever let's just
silly right like there's a lot of stuff
that comes out of major universities
that empirically works like we test it
and it makes better computers like it
works there's no question it's a
real thing
and um and then on the other side the
idea that there's this
perfect beautiful thing called the peer
review in the halls of academia that
just does the perfect epistemics and
there's no ego or bias or fight and the
finances that influence the nature of
what's being researched don't play a
role at all
that's just silly right and there's so
much stuff now where we have seen
people that are actively falsifying and
up their research or even where
they're not doing that
but like somebody put something that is
gibberish on purpose into peer review
and it gets published in an article
in a place like nature and people peer
review stuff based on
uh the politics of who is going to
who they need to get on the good side of
for their own career advancement
and then even things like okay well even
if something isn't wrong
the things that are getting funded are
the things that somebody wants to fund
because they see that there will be an
roi
on that and there might be other things
that would be more true and more
relevant that will never get funded
because there's no roi so then we say
the preponderance of data
shows such and such but it was the
preponderance of data all in this one
little area of the whole picture based
on
incentives so it's misinforming even if
it's all true
right so then we have to say like
does the fact that science needs funded
and is done by people with egos
and with politics involved does that
up the epistemics of it yeah of
course it does
and it doesn't completely it up so
ultimately
for me i actually go
into the science article i look at the
methodology i look at if the methodology
makes sense i try to
look at all of the literature and try to
do kind of structured literature review
then i try to find
experts in the field who disagree and
see if i can find out why they disagree
take the perspectives and i can start to
make sense of it
right so are
are the people who say just trust the
institutions are they right no
the who got this wrong from the
beginning again and again like they
like it's almost a perfect record of
getting things wrong
and um and many of the main universities
that were doing epidemiological models
were like
bad they're pretty bad and um
so we should just trust the authorities
as just silly that's just not paying
attention
on the other hand um
and you know we can see the who and the
gates foundation and places like that
doing randomized control trials on
antivirals
for use in the intensive case which is
once people are in hospitals
when in the entire field of medicine
antivirals almost
only work immediately after exposure not
once you already have a severe illness
and so it's like that doesn't even why
would they
why would anyone even do that trial that
doesn't even make sense
i mean yes you might want to see if that
if like by surprise it helps late stage
people because that'd be cool
but also include early stage which is
where there's really only any chance
but if you do late stage and then say it
doesn't work and generalize it as if the
early stage
maybe you're just really
being kind of dull and not paying
attention to the entire body of
antiviral knowledge
well maybe or maybe you want to show
that the
trump was an idiot and do us do an
information warfare piece that attacks
hydroxychloroquine
or maybe because you're a democrat or
supporter or
just hate him or whatever it is or maybe
you
have a drug that you really like and the
generic drugs that nobody's going to
make any money on it would be better to
show her ineffective
now are people that up
yeah like that kind of information
warfare is a real thing
and so it's important to know
that the information we're being exposed
to
has agendas attached to it and the
agendas are not always the ones they say
they are the agendas are usually complex
so um now then the other side that says
the entire thing
is nonsense this is basically a flu
nobody's really dying
that's also just gibberish and all you
have to do is
call some icu doctors in new york and
ask about their experience or in italy
and you'll never say that again
which i i did
you know early on was talking to them
working with it um
and so how was that like how was that
what did they say
they were describing seeing uh
disease progression that was unlike
anything that they had seen before the
whole ground glass opacities in the lung
the
rate at which people would degrade and
break down
the complete failure of ventilation to
do what
they would normally think it to do with
pneumonias um
you know they were very boggled by the
pathology it wasn't it didn't follow
anything that they could make sense of
it all and then they were also
completely devastated just
putting people on intubation and taking
them off dead all day
um and having to go in without ppe
and without adequate ppe and having to
like
yeah we're it's a trip because if
the doctors or nurses who decide to go
work
mostly would quarantine themselves at a
hotel and someone just staying in their
car whatever because they don't want to
go back by their family and possibly
kill their family but that also means
that they know that they might be
leaving their children parentless
because they don't want to leave these
people dying so like it's intense
and there's a massive disrespect to that
whole thing when you just say the whole
thing was a
farce because you didn't even do the
research deep enough to try to figure it
out
now
that side though that says the whole
thing is a farce because
uh of just some control agenda
are there control agendas yes of course
there are
and the thing is not to vars and it is
being utilized opportunistically the
whole don't ever let a crisis
good don't let a good crisis go to waste
well
if if i'm
playing the market when the market has
more volatility if i'm one of the better
players that has more insight i'm going
to do a lot better than when the market
doesn't have volatility
and so a few people have made a ton
of money in the last couple months when
almost everybody lost a lot of money
like
the movement of trillions of dollars it
basically concentrated
and so if i'm a major financial player
in the hedge fund world or whatever and
i
have intelligence briefings it tells me
this thing is jumped out of wuhan and
it's going to the world up whenever
could i with all of my money and
connections try
to talk to the cdc and the who and the
president whatever and get them to do a
better job of handling this well i could
i probably could succeed at that but i'm
not going to because that's not my job
and i'm not motivated to do that my
fiduciary responsibility to shareholders
anyways is to maximize profit i'm about
to
and short this market completely sell
the stocks at the top and then buy
back up at the bottom for you know a
fraction of what it was worth
a couple months ago and will be worth
again very soon
now in the same way that market
volatility creates the opportunity for
more power grabs
it also creates the opportunity
increased volatility in
in the world creates an opportunity for
more political power grabs
and so before this happened china was
trying to advance the belt and road
initiative and
russia was trying to get eastern europe
back into
deeper alliance with it and a couple
different forces in the us were pretty
focused on fighting each other for
uh the u.s power grab and so then when
this situation comes they just keep
doing the thing they were doing just
using the increased
volatility of trillions of dollars of
stimulus money and who can get it
and um and like that but that
also then ends up influencing media
narratives and even what science is
getting funded and
so um
and so then we look at things like
contact tracing okay well we have to do
diagnostics so that we can stop the
spread of the disease but then if
someone tests positive we want to know
everyone that they've interacted with
so that we can go test them as well
because otherwise
you'll have you know a single person
who's asymptomatic
can reinfect the whole world so
we're going to
empower some kind of
phone-based app to do contact tracing
should people be concerned about that
from a civil liberties
surveillance point of view absolutely
like that's a really terrible thing that
shouldn't happen
in that way and it's a really valuable
thing and these are both true
right like i think we need contact
tracing
and i don't want high-tech surveillance
that will never be removed afterwards
because if you look i mean i'll speak to
the us here because i know it better
when an emergency happens we will we'll
usually put in a provisional emergency
act to deal a wartime type act
but we don't repeal it after the
thing's over hardly ever because once
power players have got more power they
don't tend to give it back
right they don't have to and everybody
else it customizes and moves on and
kardashians or whatever um and
so the fisa act or the patriot actor the
homeland security act of the
like those don't don't roll away okay so
after 9 11 and we realized they didn't
really have weapons of mass destruction
do we roll those acts back
no and so is that this type of situation
again but where we even start getting
into
wanting to breach people's biomedical
security and be able to determine
whether they can travel or not based on
whether they
to have antibodies or vaccinated or i
think that's
really dangerous and i think we need to
do contact tracing
now i think we do low-tech contact
tracing just like we did with epidemics
throughout all of history where you just
ask people who did you come in contact
with and i think there are certain
forms of contact tracing technologically
that are much safer
and i think there are ways to put forced
expiries in them
right but this is where it's like if you
hear
let's say you're kind of left oriented
and you hear the guys who are saying
this is just a big hoax
and they just want to surveil us they're
partly right
now what they're saying as is is
actually very dangerous and pernicious
and problematic
but they're also kind of partly right
which is
are there agendas that are seeking to
advance the asymmetric power they
already have in the situation
and we should watch out for it yes of
course
and typically when you see that power
follows a power law distribution right
you'll have a few people who have most
of the power and then progressively less
the people who got here didn't get it by
sharing their power
like that's not that's not how that
happened they got it by winning a game
theory again and again and again and
again and getting good at doing that
thing right
so typically those who have more power
asymmetric power and a power law
distribution
use their asymmetric power to protect
and get more asymmetry of power
like that's the generator function and
they're fighting against other people
who are also trying to do it so
you know is it going to be zuckerberg or
is it going to be xi ji ping who gets
the metcalf law
one ring to rule them all that creates
the digital currency that is the new
reserve currency for the world
um so then you can even have the
plausible deniability of saying well i
have to do this
otherwise the other guy is going to do
the thing right
now that still looks like those with the
most power using that radical asymmetric
power to concentrate more power
does that tend to be in the good of
everyone no will we
give one example where it seems to be in
the good of everyone as the source of
selling point the sugar that makes the
medicine go down
sure so
this is when we talk about perspective
seeking and the faulty confidence
i only see faulty confidence in
kind of mainstream narratives because
mostly they live at too
low a complexity level to
make adequate sense of reality
but i mean with increased understanding
of complexity
automatically i feel your level of
confidence goes down
because the moment you start reaching a
level of complexity of understanding how
many potential factors go into it
you understand how many factors you
don't even have a proper clue about
yes now you start to become
so there was a mayor of a california
city who
contacted me today and it was so
refreshing it was one of the few
politicians that didn't
elicit um upset emotions in me
um so she was lovely and she said like i
don't even know what i don't know about
this topic i don't even know what
questions to ask i don't know how to
think about it
i don't want to waste your time but you
know like i want to make sense of it
and i'm like i'm so glad that you're the
mayor
because someone who seems earnestly like
they really care
and really wants to do the right thing
and knows that they don't know and is
seeking
to find the right source of input
can be trusted with leadership
in the doubt itching again
you can almost read it you can read it
as a book of religion or
a book of leadership or a book of um
political philosophy and they're all
true but you can read as a book of
leadership
and it kind of has this gist that says
the person who wants to lead everybody
should run away from
and that's the kind of like those who
get asymmetric power because they
pursued the out of it who use it to
keep receiving the out of it right
um but those who really don't want to
lead
and everyone pushes them to lead because
everyone trusts them so much
you can probably trust them right so
uh there is some relationship to the
certainty and uncertainty thing in that
as well
so let's say for instance we look at the
epidemiology
when we open back up is it going to
spike again are we going to get hurt
immunity
i'll give you just the tiniest example
of
some elements of the complexity that i'm
paying attention to
so the binary narrative of this is
basically airborne aids
and it's just going to keep killing
everyone until we get a vaccine
or um
or it was overblown hype and we're
already over it and we should just
release the restrictions are both
just so silly and yet what is actually
true is pretty complex
so when you look at how hard an
area gets hit what are the factors well
how many cases arrived there originally
before it was known
is going to be a factor what was the
viral load of those cases was it a light
viral load or a serious viral load and
what was the
were they super spreaders or not in
terms of what type of interaction
were they getting into what was the
population density and the population
dynamics what were the background
demographics in terms of age and mixing
across ages and comorbidities
was it an area that had high
environmental pollution of the types
that would already create lung
problems did they have previous
vaccinations because there's some
indication that those who got flu
vaccines last year got more
serious covid and that some people who
got vaccinations of other types
in the third world it might actually be
slightly protected against covid
uh there's some indication that people
who got one of the coronaviruses last
year
actual the normal four strains of
chronovirus
actually are getting coveted worse so
the antibodies are not only not
protective but priming a cytokine storm
so then we would have to ask did that
area have a previous bad coronavirus as
part of its flu season
what types of interventions did the area
put in place how early did it put those
interventions in place what are the
cultural dynamics regarding hygiene and
closeness
of contact and things like that that
would already be part of
you know mitigating the differences it's
a lot of variables and
all of a lot of those variables are like
a tiny change in an exponent makes a
pretty big difference over a little
period of time
so a lot of those are exponent variables
or
near thresholds um now we didn't even
get into mutations yet
but could it be that some of the areas
that are hit much harder than others
actually correspond to more and less
virulent mutations
yes that that is not well enough known
yet but is
we'll know it soon right being tracked
and so
if you look at one area that seems
now then we also even say well but how
many people are actually infected well
what tests are we doing
yeah that's that's the part i want to
ask you about actually about the testing
yeah so if we're only testing sick
people and then trying to estimate of
course we have
we have no background idea and then if
we're trying to test other places what
are the other places that actually give
us relevant background information
because if the people are coming out and
interacting
they might already be a higher risk
population than the people who aren't
coming out and interacting and
right so it's like how do you get
appropriate sample that's one question
then what are the false negatives and
false positives of the type of test
methodology that i'm using
and um
if i'm using amino assays
am i we have some evidence coming out of
china that about 30
of the people who have the disease were
really pretty sure they had the disease
like they had the symptomology and pcr
showed that they have the disease about
of them don't produce antibodies so
um that's not even about a false
negative false negative means when
they're producing antibodies the test
doesn't pick it up
this is that they just aren't even doing
it right we also know that
let's say that you you got chronovirus
today
you got sarge cove too today you
wouldn't be producing antibodies for
some period of time we'll call it 10
days because
it's got to go through the mucosal
system into the blood the blood's got to
produce enough antibodies
test picks it up so we wouldn't even
call that a false negative yet because
it's not
it's not that the antibodies in the
blood and the test just isn't sensitive
enough it's that it's too early in the
disease progression but you might be
infectious that entire time
right then there's some question if some
of the original
tests that got released had a bunch of
false positives because
they actually reacted with antibodies
from the previous coronaviruses that
people have been exposed to
and so some of the things about oh much
higher background rate and so that we're
already closer to saturation
then we have to say well does saturation
mean anything even because
is immunity being conferred we don't
know if immunity is being conferred
right now
so all ideas on herd immunity are
premature at this point
you can date whatever date this is that
we're talking because
are there people who
got covid got better and then had it
again
yes a lot like five to ten percent of
people in the hubei province
and in in um south korea and japan
now do we know that it's the same strain
as opposed to one strain than another
chain we don't know
amino assays won't even tell you that
right most of the
the types of amino acids do we know that
they fully got rid of it
and then they got it again exogenously
versus their viral load just went down
and then resurged
without ever having fully got rid of it
we don't know the answer to those things
right
now when people say oh well this will
can when you you have the antibodies so
of course you're immune
no there are there are viruses that
you'll produce antibodies too that don't
produce
immunity and there are some viruses
where the second time you get it is much
worse like dengue fever
right um and obviously with
ebola or hiv or hep c our answer wasn't
hurt immunity right our answer was
stop the suppression of it um
and so it tends to be that herd immunity
will be our answer for respiratory
things that are very hard to suppress
because they're respiratory
things
and that are part of the evolutionary
background that we've been exposed to
but
if it's novel right meaning we we didn't
co-evolve with this thing
then uh how long will it take to produce
effective antibodies
is a very like unknown question and so
you could even get to where you have a
saturation of the population and
then now you could also have a situation
where
someone produces antibodies and
you you can't think of everyone the same
like like we said about 30
of the people who weren't producing
meaningful number of antibodies
and so it might be that some people do
produce an antibody response that can
for some immunity and some don't
and that you might have a gaussian
distribution or some other kind of
distribution across the population
you might also have that there was one
chinese study that showed that older
people were producing about 5x 3 to 5x
more antibodies than younger people
which would be opposite of what we'd
want to see it could so that could
actually mean that it is priming an
immune response that is of the more
cytokine storm type that makes it worse
um there are ways we could figure this
out but it hasn't happened yet
and now also as it's mutating are we
going to have a worse round to follow up
like happened with 1918
uh spanish flu
well we won't be able to know perfectly
but we can look at the nature of how
it's mutating so far
which regions have good error correction
in them etc and start to make some good
forecasts
but i would say there's still massive
unknowns in there
then what happens when co when sars cove
2 and influenza hit at the same time in
this next flu season
we don't know and so all of
so the right answer is
this is a pretty complex multi-factorial
thing there's
and whether people get immunity or not
and whether the immunity
lasts for two years or only two months
and whether the immunity will be
effective against
meaningful mutations or not and whether
it's mutating or not
and whether it's the same for the whole
population or only for parts of the
population and whether it primes a worse
secondary response and
um and if we came up with a vaccine
because we saw that the influenza
vaccine that people did last year it
looks like produced about a 25 percent
more severe response than people who got
covered because it was
shunting the immune in function in a
particular direction
might we actually make a vaccine for
this that doesn't protect against a
mutation actually primes them to be
worse that are already more lethal ones
there's a lot of pretty important
unknowns
so you want to do is list them all right
and then say what kind of research do we
need to do to figure these things out
and how do we coordinate the
international research efforts and how
do we make sure the methodology is
appropriate
and how do we coordinate a global exit
strategy
because there really are no national
exit strategies right
if herd immunity is a thing maybe
there's a national exit strategy
but otherwise we
the no country gets to return to normal
if it doesn't get an open trade and
travel back up
and given that only one person who's
asymptomatic has to have it to
re-trigger the whole thing
this is a uniquely interconnecting for
the whole world situation
right and we know that what works in
vienna isn't going to be the solution
for
india and bangladesh just because of
cost per capita and yet
a solution that doesn't work for india
in bangladesh keeps vienna unsafe
or unable to open it's like okay so we
need a global exit strategy
and we can think about that like what
are the various types of exit herd
immunity would be one well we got to
answer the questions to see is that even
a thing
right and if it's not a thing right now
can we make it a thing can we make it to
where
are there things that we can do to help
prime people's immune system
to have better immune responses right
what about vaccination similarly we
haven't succeeded at vaccines for the
four coronaviruses that have been around
forever there's a lot of
viruses that took us a very long time to
find effective vaccines and things like
the flu that mutate a lot
don't work for uh the ongoing mutation
so does that mean that this is a new
thing that we just have forever and have
to
take new you know vaccines for forever
so with the unknowns there then we say
well maybe we'll just the end
the end state is suppression we just
have to diagnose
everyone and contact trace to just fully
suppress it
ebola it's really hard with something
that is asymptomatic for possibly
weeks or months or forever and some
people and
yet they're infectious like that's kind
of uniquely terrible
as far as contagion goes and how are you
gonna really contact trace and diagnose
everyone in bangladesh um like
that's a pretty serious technological
rollout you know
per capita dollar wise so
then we start saying well we can some
amount of that has to happen right
there's we definitely want to suppress
where we can
but also the herd immunity answer
affects that right
now animals are getting it and we live
with the animals if the animals can
store it do we ever get to full
suppression if it's zoonotic and can
keep
passing back now and and our cats and
dogs and are getting it
well that's that's a whole there's more
variables right
so then we get into the management well
how do we treat it can we make it to
where
it really is only as bad as the flu the
early stage antiviral makes it not that
bad
well the exit strategy those are like
clusters of exit strategies and
they some are better than others but
only if they're true and in order to be
true there's
we have to figure out so what we
need is a
coordinated approach for the entire
world to come up with an exit strategy
great as easy as that well
we've got a couple more parts we have to
make sure that our exit strategy will
also be good for follow-up mutation
rounds that could occur
and follow up pandemics because we're in
a situation where that
could be a thing again in time right and
they could be more lethal this
we were lucky that this one wasn't more
lethal than it was so we have to also be
creating ongoing pandemic infrastructure
we also have to make sure that we aren't
making the world worse by the nature of
our solution
so that we don't create radically
up autocracies and surveillance states
and increase surveillance capitalism
and decrease people's uh health privacy
or do rushed vaccines where we didn't do
long-term safety studies that stuff
up
so we all we have to solve the problem
set up infrastructure for the next
rounds of the problem
make sure we don't make worse
at minimum and then hopefully also
set up more competent responses for
other types of catastrophes
which are also impending and deal with
the second and third order effects that
have already started from this right we
already have had
a breakdown in the food supply because
of this right so
india northern africa southeast asia but
also in the united states
the animal husbandry were culling huge
numbers of chickens and pork and
whatever because they
can't be sold because they're sold to
fast food restaurants and
then people starving in other areas
these are supply chain intelligence
breakdown issues for
two billion people's food supply just
got up um
and the u.s china tensions
in terms of superpower war just
radically increased in geopolitical
tensions in the eu
and whatever so we also have to solve
those issues and prevent the worse
escalations from happening
now thinking about it through the lens
of militarism
right increased conflict escalation
between state actors
or just increasing violence within
states from non-state actors of people
who
feel really like their government is
suppressing them are really upset or
whatever
so thinking through the lens of conflict
escalation
and violence escalation is a type of
perspective to take
right and then within that taking a
uniquely chinese perspective or a
russian perspective or
u.s perspective or an eu or particular
country are also going to give very
different insights
taking the perspective of finance or
economics or supply chains
or the global south in poverty or
the info ecology and journalism or all
of those
or cyber warfare or medicine or what
life is like inside the icu
to actually be able to sense make it
well enough to come up with solutions
all of those are perspectives that have
to be
well understood do you have the feeling
that
current governments do that or to what
degree
do you think they do that
well so governments have government
agencies that are designed to look at
different things right they have
agencies that look at logistics and
supply chains and look at
national security threats of different
types and
look at uh
regulation of news and various things so
the question is how well
do they do it and to call governments a
class
and unify across them would be silly
because it's a pretty radical
distribution between
how well some do it and others as a
function of lots of things
partly as a function of
how small the country is and how
homogeneous the population and the kind
of gdp per capita of it and
historical things and how established
the culture is
uh all of those things all augment the
nature of the government and what kinds
of
wars and overhauls and did it go
through it so we could
do that by a country by country basis
but um
the big countries
like china does a very good job of
coordinating all of the stuff
but i can't say they do a good job of
coordinating it
for the interest of the world they do a
good job
i can't even say they do a good job of
coordinating it for the interest of
china
this and i won't say china does a good
job i'll say the ccp
does a very good job of coordinating
lots of functions in a top-down way
probably the best job in the world right
now
and they do it in a way that is good for
the ccp and its vision of china
the us completely sucks at it
um the us's
you know it's it's undergone such
intensive institutional decay
and democracies typically last two to
three hundred years we're coming up on
250 years
you know it's uh this looks like
what an empire about to fall looks like
where it's so divided amongst itself
that it's not paying attention to the
outside world adequately
so china's advancing the belt and road
initiative
in terms of being able to be on the
other side of this issue and bring ppe
and medical supplies to other places in
the world and we can't even
figure out how to deal with it for
ourselves and get ppe to our own
hospital workers
and inside the us you have a very strong
kind of like
establishment versus trump insurgency
thing that are fighting for
the power capture in the u.s because the
power is so big
and while they're doing it not being
geopolitically strategic enough
um or doing a good job of actually
tending to the people or the crisis or
whatever
um yeah we could talk about different
places but
and um what do you think would be the
most
relevant things to tackle right now to
improve that
or the the best um
yeah parts to put energy towards to
[Music]
clarify that question for me um so if
you observe okay
like america is doing a terrible job at
that right now
um what do you think would be the things
to prioritize right now like where do
you think would be the energy well
most spent on or how would you approach
if you would be the president of the
united states
how would you approach it okay i want to
make sure i understand the question
right
what are the most important things to
respond to covid
as the president of the united states or
how could we actually
correct newest governance and reverse
the institutional deplay
so it doesn't it would naturally have
the capacity to do a good job with
anything
i i was um the first part was more
around the corvette response
but i would like to lead into a general
structure of a governance
okay some things i'd like to see the u.s
doing
i would like to see the u.s
working with all of its international
allies to lead a global exit strategy
and that identifies the various
types of exits that might be
and coordinates the world's scientific
research happening at all the different
institutions towards making sure that
they're not duplicating similar research
they're not withholding the research or
not having it synthesized in a central
place
there aren't critical topics that are
getting
under addressed and white space being
left so i would have a
international coalition effort towards
global exit strategy
it would identify what the types of
exits could be
and what needs to be known to figure
those out
and then be coordinating the research
towards that that's one thing
in the meantime that alliance effort
would also
work with
all of the groups all the countries that
want to ally which is not just european
allies but
japan and south korea and singapore and
vietnam and other countries that
did a better job of this than we did and
went through sars cove one and other
things and like they just have this
more figured out than we do and you know
most of the countries i just mentioned
are wealthy countries and like high-tech
countries like
so to not include japan and south korea
and singapore and an alliance effort
would just be silly especially given
uh their relationship with china and
ours and the tensions and whatever
and an alliance effort to get
ppe medical supply and support to
all of the countries that are later than
us in the curve
and information to them uh and
particularly
many of the poorer countries because
there is no solution that isn't a
solution for everybody on this thing
and if china is the major exporter of
solutions that's going to result in a
particular kind
of world order and
this has nothing to do with the chinese
people or chinese history or chinese
culture
but the current government
that uses um
radically technologically advanced
autocracy
is just not the type of global
governance we want for the world
right we want to suppress that wherever
it happens
in the u.s in china and wherever which
is also why i'm saying this needs to be
an alliance effort so that nobody gets
to do the power grab
but the us is in the best position to
lead it if it
really did the good thing that it could
do right
um
i would definitely like to see
uh the internal
i would like to see some major effort
towards protecting the upcoming
elections and be able to show that
uh be able to create confidence across
the
both parties and across everyone that
the election was not going to be
manipulated rigged or stolen
and create the kinds of process and
transparency to do that it's a long
discussion of how to do that but it so
obviously needs done
um and then with that secured
really work for uh
not narrative politics stuff but
bipartisan cooperation towards
um pandemic solution
there's a there's a lot of things that
the us so i think that the us needs to
roll out
very high tech pcr diagnostics pretty
ubiquitously
so that um we can see it very early
stage with very high sensitivity
and be able to both isolate and start
treating right away so the economy can
open back up without spreading the
pandemic vector again
uh it should be investing very heavily
in early stage treatment
so that when people do get it they don't
have to wind up in the icu
with serious illness um
so a lot of early stage treatment
research they should prioritize
existing drugs not new drugs
um so hydroxychloroquine was actually a
right thing to look at
and ivermectin and methylene blue and
pde inhibitors and a bunch of the ones
that
have been around for a long time a new
drug
we have no long-term safety data on so
it might not kill you or do some like
this is one of the interesting things is
we will look for some signs of safety
we'll look at liver enzymes and a few
things but we don't know what stuff to
look for
right there's a lot of biometrics you
could track in a body
so under a pandemic you might be tempted
to rush the normal process
but rushing the normal process on a new
thing where we have no long-term safety
data is very different than
drugs that have been around for 20 or 50
or 70 years we have a ton of safety
data and all we're trying to find is new
application right i'm totally happier to
rush
a new application of a known safety
profile
i want to rush new drugs less and i want
to rush vaccines even less
because unlike small molecule drugs
vaccines are intended to have permanent
effects
and so i really want to make sure
they're the right permanent effects
right if they're intending to modulate
the immune system
lastingly then of
all the drugs that you want to do
long-term safety studies on vaccines the
most important
and
so yes ubiquitous diagnostics contact
tracing i would like to see them doing
uh employing a hundred thousand people
which people need employed anyways to do
contact tracing
um that don't require everyone
activating their bluetooth
or the things like that that open up
hacking and intelligence community
issues and surveillance of different
types i would
um
i would like to see the
distribution of medical supplies and ppe
and resources like that happen at a
federal level
um they don't have to override state
sovereignty and control the states to
support the states with supply chain
capacities that our federal government
has historically done
i'd like to see that and um
obviously the economic stimulus needs
handled quite differently
um i i actually actually want to lead
over to
um second and third
uh order effects of kovid and the
responses
because i really really appreciate your
insights into the interconnectedness of
different topics and how things
uh yeah how things on a global scale as
well are
are connected but also through sectors
so how do you perceive
or what do you perceive as the most
relevant uh second and third tier
or other effects of of kovi
now that you've mentioned financial i
think that's probably going to be one of
the
um the areas that are going to be really
if really affected by it
well there's super obvious ones and then
there's ones that are a little bit less
obvious and then there's ones that we
don't know what
is going to happen so
one pretty obvious pretty bad one we
mentioned
was uh the food supply
um when you
try to stop travel to stop a virus you
can also break
supply chains and in this case you break
the supply chain of pesticides for areas
that do monocrop agriculture and depend
upon those and that's the only way they
can control the locusts
and you end up getting these massive
numbers of locusts throughout northern
africa and parts of the middle east that
destroy all the crops and
under quarantine not letting uh
farmers and distributors and would ever
be able to work so food is rotting in
the fields and
um and similarly so many of the major
agricultural producers
of uh potatoes
uh chicken pork eggs whatever
are used to selling to a small number of
vendors they sell to mcdonald's
and the mcdonald's says the distribution
throughout its network and people aren't
going to mcdonald's
the people still need the food they just
they're not getting at mcdonald's
mcdonald's isn't doing it
and the and the farms aren't or the
agricultural manufacturers i won't call
them farms
aren't set up to get it directly to the
people so they're just
like in the u.s they're culling millions
of animals just killing the animals and
throwing
throwing them out burying potatoes and
food and whatever
while there are millions of people with
no access to food
you know you you've got hundreds of
millions of people who have very bad
food security in
india right now a bunch of people
starving in sub-saharan africa you have
people in refugee camps who can't leave
who don't have food
but even in the us and el paso you have
these miles long
lines of cars waiting for food and so
can violence happen because of that
pretty quickly yeah
that could kill a lot more people than
kovit ever would have killed
so that's a very serious issue now
that's a second order effect
right can the violence lead to war
can the war escalate as larger third
order effects yeah
and you know when you start to look at
existing political tensions and where
high technological military power is
you know one of the ones i'm most
concerned about is india
because if
millions or tens or hundreds of millions
of people stop having access to food
do they just die peacefully or do they
start to go into resource wars
if they go into resource wars how does
it cleave well probably along
existing tension lines might that look
like muslim hindu lines
especially in northern parts of india
could that lead to an india-pakistan war
right like these are nuclear-equipped
countries so that's one example but
there's a lot of those
types of examples
we also have breakdown in the supply
chains of medical equipment
and medicines that's a pretty huge deal
we have
the i the true idea
that dollars are dirty right that cash
is actually a vector for disease
transmission of a disease that lives on
surfaces
and to increase the impetus that was
already there by
a number of actors towards a digital
currency
a digital currency is a massive
power play
because let's say we look at the digital
currency that china's been working to
roll out
as much as you would think that there
are issues with something like wechat or
whatever that is a
a very state engaged company
it still has some degree of autonomy as
a company
but this is basically a digital currency
issued by
the chinese communist party directly
which means that
like there's anonymity in cash right
nobody
actually knows where i spend my cash
with a digital currency it is a
perfected financial surveillance
apparatus to know exactly how much money
i have where it is which accounts i move
it to when
everything else right so of course
governments want that right like a lot
of governments would want that to make
sure tax evasion isn't happening and
whatever
and if you really trusted your
government to be totally awesome you
might be okay with that but
this whole power corrupts absolute power
corrupts absolutely thing keeps
stuff up
and um so
then there is a we know that people
don't want a bunch of different
currencies
and what is the world reserve currency
so then we also start looking at the
the oil price shocks right
and seeing oil get down to a negative
price is this unprecedented thing
but besides the fact that that's a huge
deal and what does it mean and
goes negative when there's not enough
storage to store the existing
oil so then is that going to lead to
somebody realizing that there's an
opportunity to
create a lot more oil storage as a
financial opportunity yes
does that mean that with the price
dropping in more oil storage we might
actually
have climate change going the worst
direction because they're starting to
have cheap oil open up whole new oil
markets
and demands start to increase in other
ways yeah totally
um what does it mean in terms of
militarism well
we know that when the price of oil drops
to almost nothing
only the companies with the most money
on hand can survive
for very long right so saudi arabia will
do fine for a while
and russia will do fine for a while as
basically major wealthy state-sponsored
oil producers
but a lot of smaller states and private
companies will start collapsing
and so then is that just a radical
concentration of power again
yeah probably and then what type of
geopolitical tensions does that create
because let's say that some smaller
country
loses their economic capability they
can't take care of their people but they
still have a military
well it's a bad position to have your
economics go to and still have a
military
because then you have to deal with it
somehow right um
so these types of geopolitical things
that we're talking about here there's a
lot of them
and you can see that then increasing
of the price of oil we start looking at
and that was that was related to the
situation there was already systemic
fragility but that was because of a
decrease in demand for oil and then the
war over increasing the supply whatever
now we could look at that moving in the
direction of affecting climate change or
in the direction of affecting
geopolitical tensions towards war or
financial concentration right this like
it branches pretty fast then we have all
the like the increase in domestic
abuse happening
like really kind of gruesome spousal and
child abuse
because there's a lot of up
people in the world and
a lot of the way that people survive is
by avoiding their family
and under this situation where they
can't you get increasing those types of
violence so then
what happens also when like the people
in new york or in italy know
everybody knows a lot of people that
died so you have like generational
trauma like happened with a great
depression or a war or whatever so then
what are the lasting societal effects of
that
lasting societal effects of um
[Music]
you know of existential fear and of kind
of more ubiquitous trauma what happens
to
a generation of kids who all lose a
pretty meaningful period of school time
um lots of lots of things like this
the domestic elections in the us are not
secure
at this point cannot be considered
secure when
trillions of dollars of new money just
get made up like what is that
and and i don't think anyone thinks
those will be really rightly distributed
to everyone
right um and but unlike in 2008
they didn't all go to the big bank usual
brokers they went to
some new brokers that seem to be more
associated with the kind of current
insurgency that's in the white house
rather than the establishment forces so
you also see like
competition at the very top of global
and u.s finance
in a way that's different so what how do
those shocks ripple out
we could go into any of those you want
but this is just giving examples of
starting to think about
what second and third order and
cascading effects look like and what
cascading effects
on systemic fragility looks like because
if you had where all the countries
didn't need import or export right they
had fully domestic economies
well it wouldn't be quite the same thing
when you have globalized supply chains
where
every single country in the world
depends upon six continent type supply
chains
and where you have tensions all over the
place and you have very powerful weapons
associated with the tensions and you
have
technologies that radically concentrate
power like digital metcalf law type
stuff and
so we're dealing with and you know i
would say if it wasn't coronavirus
something else would have done the same
thing
it could have easily been like the fires
that happened in australia
that were partly related to the climate
that was dry and hot
that dry hot thing similarly hitting
india and driving food death there for
that reason
could have led to this whole thing or
what was happening in the amazon that
could break the hydrological pump and
affect the
rainfall for north america basically we
just needed something big enough
to start to set off the systemic
fragilities
the systemic abilities haven't always
been there because it's unique to
globalization
it's unique to
you know up until world war ii we didn't
have technology big enough to up
everything
like we tried to up everything like
that you look at genghis khan and
alexander the great and the romans like
we would use our technology to
up
for personal gain and but how much stuff
we could destroy was limited by how
powerful we were world war ii was when
we were like oh we actually have the
power to make the whole
place uninhabitable well in evolutionary
time that's just like a minute ago
and we made this entire world system the
whole bretton woods world the world bank
and the
u.n and everything to make sure we never
used that power
right that we didn't use the nukes again
but nukes are super hard to make
right your enriching uranium is super
hard to do you can monitor it from
satellites the uranium doesn't exist in
that many places
and so when you have two superpowers and
one catastrophe weapon
you can do mutually assured destruction
and make sure nobody uses it
but when you start getting to drone
weapons and ai controlled drone weapons
and bio weapons and
um all of the other kind of exponential
tech media weapons that are not that
hard to make
and you have a world today where you've
got dozens of catastrophe weapons held
by
many dozens of actors that can't even
all be monitored
you can't do mutual destruction on that
and when bretton woods happened
we weren't near the planetary limits of
growth we hadn't already taken
most of the fish out of the ocean or
up the coral or got close to the
tipping points on the amazon or any of
those types of things
so we could just say let's just base
finance ourselves out of this by
printing so much money and
exploiting whatever we need you to print
so much money that we don't have to
fight because we just keep
having so much positive some growth you
don't get to do that forever
right so we really are at a tipping
point where
we've reached planetary boundaries
and that creates its own fragility we
have these globalized supply chains
where collapse anywhere can create
collapse in other places we saw a little
problem in wuhan and the whole
world is affected right so
radically interconnected world and
where too many people have too big a
weapons
and not just the kinetic weapons but
even the effect on everyone's psyche of
technologies like facebook
and google that either we've become
powerful enough
relative to the now smallness of our
world and our own developmental
innate capacities that we either figure
out how to use that power
much much much better or we blow
ourselves up with it
so that's the omni lose-lose scenario
you've been talking about around
that in the end if you keep enforcing
the win-lose scenarios of one
one party trying to advance at the cost
of the other it's just eventually going
to lead to us destroying
the place we live in basically yeah and
that's why it needs change
yeah there is a you know
that kind of uh
win-lose game theory not only
like the first thing is that
historically it actually worked like we
actually could kill the other guys and
get the riverfront property that they
had and that was awesome right
and then they stopped competing with us
for for hunting and whatever
but it wasn't just that it worked it was
obligated
because if we just wanted to be peaceful
but
they're going out killing other tribes
and taking their
then we have to militarize ourselves to
defend ourselves or we lose by default
as soon as anyone militarizes which is
why
some of the more peaceful cultures just
got slaughtered by the warring cultures
and the effective warring cultures
taught each other to war better and you
get this upregulation of war capacity
where anybody comes out with a new
weapon and everybody has to create
counter weapons and new better weapons
right
so you get this but ultimately that's an
exponential curve
that drives an exponential curve and
it's all externalizing harm on a finite
common space
and so we've been in a place where like
that has worked
what has worked and has even been
obligated
as a mode itself will now create
the self-termination and so
we need a fundamentally different
approach than civilization has ever
done or or been able to implement
previously
which requires to understand
or to be able to to
understand that equilibrium right
because if you if you don't if you don't
look at that time scale
then you're just going to still see that
that win
scenario for you right
and you know one of the interesting
things the whole
[Music]
think globally act locally idism
most people are doing the opposite of
that without realizing it
where they're thinking about how to
protect their own job and how to get a
bonus and get ahead and
advance in their social circle and
whatever it is like they're thinking
about some pretty local
right but they're buying stuff that
comes from supply chains that happened
run by warlords and on six continents
backed up by militaries and pursuing
dollars that are basically contracts
backed up by militaries that and that
support militaries
so they're and they're buying their food
that comes from the factory farms
that both create swine flues and bird
flus and pandemics
and create massive slaughtering in the
environment and they don't even realize
but they're causing it so it's like
who's causing it well i am
i'm acting globally in really atrocious
ways for my local optimization and not
even knowing it
um go ahead what do you do what do you
do currently to
bring to raise more awareness regarding
that or
or what's your current mission
so i
had a series of processes uh in my life
of realizing that
things that i cared about and wanted to
solve were connected to other things
that i didn't know that i cared about
but that also had to be solved until it
come
it came to
if i try to stop these animals from
being poached by
putting bigger fences but the poachers
are still broke and have the same
mindset they go
poach some other animal that might even
be more endangered right like
how in order to really address it we
have to actually address
not only the interconnectedness but what
are the driving functions underneath it
and i also went through the process of
trying to like assuming at first naively
that there were approaches already in
place that were probably good
or adequate that started with activism
you know in the kind of ngo world and
then
kind of looking at the maybe un igo
world and then seeing if maybe there
were economic solutions if the austrian
school or the anarcho-capitalist figured
it out or if the scandinavian model
could apply
or the um permaculture for the whole
world whatever right like
and it was clear that they all had some
good partial insights but it could run
the fail cases of why no this
this actually isn't a solution for this
whole problem set
so i kept trying to understand the
nature of the problems better to be able
to see what would an adequate solution
look like
or a set of solutions and
and the question like a central question
is always very orienting is what is
most needed for civilization and life to
thrive that is not being tended to
currently
and that both is looking that requires a
clear sense of what's needed
right it requires what understanding the
the current problems and the future risk
spaces
and both what isn't addressed and what
the highest
leverage types of things are in that
stack would say that there's kind of
three primary horizons in my current
focus
uh there's what you can think of as the
nearer term stuff
which is that there's a bunch of
catastrophic risks
that if they happen we won't be able to
reverse
and they'll just suck so bad we must do
everything we can to have them not
happen
and they're currently eminent or
um have high enough probability that
the probability is radically lowered and
even though they're being driven by
underlying systems they're being driven
by perverse incentive within the nature
of
how our market and government systems
interact and they're being driven by
poor sense-making and
political power games whatever we're not
going to be able to fix those underlying
systems fast enough we just have to
solve these things kind of directly
and so there's a whole set of ecological
things that are actually pretty near
tipping points
where without fixing the underlying
systems that generate the problem we
just have to keep them from happening
we need to keep large-scale war from
happening we need to pay attention to
the very large-scale refugee
issues that could happen in the next
little while there's some grid stability
grid collapse stuff right there's a
handful of things like that
there's also certain kinds of power
consolidation that if they happen we'll
probably never get out of
and that are really bad so we need to
keep some of those things from happening
so this is the like triage bucket it's a
pretty big bucket
right like any one of those pretty big
thing but it's how do we identify
all the ways that humanity could go off
the rails near term
and there's a kind of risk assessment to
be able to see what the escalation
pathways to various kinds of
irreversible risks are and say how do we
close those
there's a another thing that has to be
happening simultaneous
there's a slightly longer arc which is
institutional change how do we work with
the existing institutions to be able to
have them be more oriented in
effective directions so how can we make
certain perverse incentives within
markets less incentivized what could we
do to make
up things more expensive and what
could we do to make things that would be
really good more profitable right can we
change the topology of the incentive
landscape where still
incentive seeking capitalism would
incent different things
and within governments
can we do things that force higher kinds
of transparency
and accountability that decrease the
corruption
and kind of self-dealing and crony
capitalism and regulatory capture
well it turns out that there is quite a
lot that can be done in those spaces
and for reasons that will take
more time than we have today i
i will say that the very best we could
do in that still won't be long-term
adequate that the underlying axioms the
underlying structures of those systems
aren't
right but the new systems that we would
want to build from scratch will
take quite a while and so we have to do
this
vectoring these systems in the right
direction because they're the systems
that still run the world right
we've got 50 or 100 trillion dollars
that trades hands every day
and so that's a lot of total activity
we have to start vectoring that thing in
the right direction as we work on new
economic systems that might not be
measured in
single fungible currencies so
that's the second category is kind of
existing institutional change
the third one is build new new
civilization systems from scratch that
are reverse engineered from defining
the problem set well enough so we
identify all the catastrophic risks that
could happen especially as we have
increasing technological power and
that power means the ability to do good
and up stuff but the
up stuff kind of ruins the whole thing
right
so um one war
ruins everybody's ability who died to do
poetry and art and all of the other
things right
so um
there is a entropic orientation right
there's an asymmetry that makes entropy
easier
just easier to break than it is to
build it and so
um so if we identify well what are all
of the ways
all the kind of catastrophic and
existential risks what are the things
that
lead us to making those things happen
what are the system dynamics and the
incentives and the
whatever so we call those the generator
functions of existential risk
and then rather than try to solve this
one and this one and this one separately
can we actually solve those generator
functions categorically which would
solve every instance in the class
as a new instantiation of a civilization
kernel can we have a situation where
the architecture of the economics has
removed perverse incentive fundamentally
so it's removed the
evolutionary niche for sociopathic
behavior
right maybe it's where there's just that
doesn't ever pay um
or corruption through the right kinds of
transparency and accounting and justice
and whatever
so that's been a focus of mine for a
bunch of years because if we couldn't
get that that totally recalibrated my
sense of the whole
possibility space and so i was fortunate
to have some really
incredible people colleagues worked
together
for quite some years on that and came to
yes it is actually possible there are
solutions
if we ask the question how do we make a
world that's anti-fragile civilization
in presence of having exponential
technology kind of available to
everybody
decentralized exponential technology
factoring the way that humans are
right so the kinds of beings that we
have been and how we have been stewards
of power
can that many of us have that much power
and have the thing be anti-fragile
it's a tough problem right it was not
obvious revolution to it
and but we did end up coming up with yes
there is actually a field of solutions
they don't look like any of the systems
we've tried so far which makes sense
right they don't look like
nation-state-based liberal democracy or
communism or
socially they look like some kind of
deeply reimagined premises but
and so there's work happening to build
those types of systems prototype them
refine them
to then be strange attractors of a new
model
and the idea would be and and the
fundamental basis of them is much higher
collective intelligence that leads to
better resource utilization and
but because of that also leads to better
innovation which also leads to them
being able to
offer things to the world that the rest
of the world needs so it engenders
healthy relationship rather than enmity
and being able to defend themselves
without needing to go offensive and
various things like that
so then what we would expect is that if
there's a radically more effective
civilization system
that other places would want to
implement it and
so you start to get a uh
an adoption based on a new attractive
basin
right but that'll take a few generations
somebody told me this story i have no
idea if anybody ever thought this was
true or not but the idea makes sense
that in the exodus story when the people
were leaving egypt and they took 40
years to do like a one month long walk
um what was that about the metaphor was
that they needed a couple generations of
people to die off for the slave
mentality to be fully gone before
starting a new civilization that
wasn't still slaves or the children of
slaves
and so there were some people that had
enough wisdom to say oh these people
are probably actually not going to be
able to let that go
and so we're going to like keep
developing new people and
at least as a metaphor there's this idea
of that there's a transition between one
system and a new system and that
transition requires some
generational shift usually so
that's why the that's why the second
category the work with the current
institutions to vector them in the right
direction because we're going to need
them for a while
so i would say the things that i'm
interested in kind of span those three
categories
and then you i uh i said in the
beginning i want to keep it
rather the 75 minutes but i
i could ask you questions without end i
think that's showcasing uh
why we had a three-hour conversation
back then in the restaurant as well
um as a
if you would have to um
or like is there is there a message that
you would like to share that you feel
um that you feel passionate about or to
the audience that you think
you would like to leave as a last
statement
i can't say that this is the most
important thing i could say but it's uh
just the first thing that came to mind
it was actually from a conversation i
was having
with a friend right before we got on
the call
um so we were talking about dialectic
earlier
so here's one dialectic that is kind of
interesting
so one of the traits of sociopathy
is not feeling a whole
category of negative emotions right not
feeling remorse or guilt or shame when
you
do something that hurts people which is
why you're a sociopath or a
psychopath or something in that cluster
b kind of category
um and
so it's it's interesting
that if people don't feel certain kinds
of negative emotions they can cause lots
more harm to other people
right because they don't feel them
vicariously
and
this also tends to be why people who are
oriented that way this is part of the
story there's also innate power seeking
tend to be in so much more positions of
power it's because they
um people who don't want to harm anyone
usually don't want to make the kinds of
decisions necessary
to win at power games um
where they don't just feel great that
they beat out the competition that means
lots of people can't feed their kids and
got laid off and
but you know they got a yacht um or the
war
advanced or whatever
now there's a lot of spiritual and
philosophic and worldview ideas that
make us a little bit like a sociopath
they're ways of numbing out pain
and whether it's uh
you know always wanting to look on the
positive side
of everything and look for the kind of
silver lining where it's actually a
denial of pain it's not wanting to be
with the reality of it and
you see this when like someone is
grieving the loss of someone close to
them and they're
hurt and the other person just can't be
with it and they instantly say well the
good side is
you know it's like shut the up
that's not the wrong thing to be saying
right now
um
but there's a lot of people who feel the
pain of the world or who feel
authentic fear or concern at these types
of risks i'm talking about
and then they just get crippled right
because they feel kind of
overwhelmed with uncertainty and fear
and sadness and despair and anger and
whatever
and so if it's the case that
the people who
see the world in a way that actually has
them
connect to the harms of others less
that that empowers them more and those
who are connected to the harms of the
world more are disempowered
then the world will continue to be run
by sociopaths
and or people who at least have some
world views that make them
sociopath-like and that's a very bad
equation
right so we need to get on the other
side of that thesis antithesis thing and
say
how can i be how can i have a real
assessment of the problems of the world
a a real assessment of the risks of the
world a real assessment of my own
uncertainty
and actually be more empowered
to act in service of the whole and
courageously and in service of what i
love
than before and it's a different kind of
power right it's not the power of how do
i
be an apex predator and not care when
everyone else is just a prey animal that
dies it's a how do i have the power to
be a steward of the whole
um that's possible it's not common
but i would say it's both possible and
it's the necessary new baseline state we
need to not
blow ourselves up with the amount of
power we have
and so if people can think about is the
way that i'm thinking about this
increasing my sense of empowerment and
increasing my sense of empathy and
responsibility for the whole
simultaneously
if it is not increasing both of them
keep rethinking about it until you find
a way that does
which is to me similar to
if you expand like i i feel every human
is
thinking about themselves um
and for me that is expanding that sense
of self
or or the things that we care about and
so
if i try like if i only see myself and
everything else i don't really care
about
then i advance myself at the cost of
everything around me
but if i if that understanding of self
if that level of consciousness is
entailing
everything around me as well and i
understand that i'm part of a system and
and
i do the best if the system is doing the
best then
now i care and then i take
responsibility for the hole rather than
just
for a virtual line that i drew in the
sand
is that me is that along the lines of
what you meant meant
well you made one step but i want to go
another step okay
so the step that you made is
um
intelligent and thoughtful reciprocal
altruism
reciprocal altruism is i do better when
the system does better and the system
other people so i'll help them because
it's good for me
rather than i'll them because i get
ahead i'll find ways that i can
where i help them i get ahead but i'm
still doing it for me
i'm still ultimately coming from a place
of
focused on you know with them what's in
it for me
i'm kind of this um miserable needy
thing that just
needs to keep getting from the
world needs to keep getting
stuff and recognition and attention and
whatever the it is
and i will do things that are nice to
the degree it gives me
like that's a starting place that at
least can make people less dreadful
to begin with but
you don't actually achieve anything like
meaningful
happiness as long as you're still
focused on what's in it for me because
you're still affirming a self that's
empty
right it's there is some sense of a
it's a misunderstanding of self that is
some sense that needs a bunch of
what you keep getting is more of that
sense of self which means no matter how
much
that you get whether it's
achievement or recognition or whatever
that same kind of sense is there which
is very different than the kind of
desire that comes from a place of
wholeness
and and then connectedness to the world
and then a recognition of the intrinsic
meaningfulness of others lives not
because supporting them will make your
life better but just because
their life actually matters to you
because you actually give a for no
selfish reason
and like you can do this thought
experiment
okay let's say that it was true that
when i die i became a guardian angel or
i had that possibility
right i'm not saying that's true it's a
thought experiment
so let's say i had that and
i don't have to do anything if i want to
just chill in heaven and listen to music
i can do that
but i have the opportunity to affect
people's lives in a positive way
sometimes but they'll never know it i
can
divert the the ball in the road where
the kid doesn't get hit by the car
this question comes do i ever do that
do i ever bother having the kid not get
hit by the car because i'm not going to
get from it
right well no i will get something i'll
get feeling better about myself
well that also already has the the
emptiness of like i don't feel good
about myself
and i have to do something like that no
when that mom is crying watching her
baby get
hit and what like i feel it not because
i need something or whatever but because
i can resonate with that
her experience is as deep to universe as
mine is
i'm not the only focal point and if i
and if i can
and i can think about that kid's life
and i can think about
the whole universe experiencing itself
through this kid
in this in these unique ways and falling
in love for the first time and
when he becomes a parent or whatever and
i'm like that's just actually beautiful
and i want to be in service to that for
no obvious reason for me at all
um i think the switch
where people start to have a sense of
wholeness that doesn't need a bunch of
stuff from other people in the world
and then can from that place of
wholeness actually show up to other
people because you care about them not
because you want to get something out of
doing something for them
that's when life starts to me
i find that a very
um very very nice and interesting
thought
it was interesting when you said when
you described it i was thinking okay but
this
sense of self then isn't really
um there's not not the separation
anymore
it's like if you're if you're relate and
if you empathize and if you feel then
it's not like you experience them it's
more like it's kind of the same
so now go back and read any scripture of
the world
and see that it was talking about that
right
love thy neighbor as thyself not as much
as what the does that mean
right and or that the naming is the
beginning of the ten thousand things in
the dao tai ching
because it's it's in okay i'm the
separate dude over here i'm daniel
you're you we're not
really i'm daniel i'm this is me this
isn't me this isn't me is that
okay so who the am i without the
planet i'm not the planet who am i
without the planet
i'm nothing who am i without the
atmosphere i'm nothing who am i without
the plants that make the atmosphere i'm
nothing
i have to take for granted that the
thing that i call me depends on
all this other stuff i have to take that
for granted to say this is me
but i don't exist without all of it
so the idea of me is just actually an
ontologically ill-formed idea
like it's just a philosophically bad
concept
i am an emergent property of this
universe
and of course there's some autonomy but
you try to take me as autonomous in the
middle of outer space with nothing and i
don't do that well
right but but then there's a case uh to
say
like if your understanding of me is
all encumbering then you want me
still to do well yeah
right like it's just a different it's
just not daniel
anymore but it's like everything and
then that is the bodhisattva impulse or
the chrystic impulse or the where the
impulse to really
serve life comes from it comes from
actually
like where the service impulse at first
it comes from some
like fear of hell or desire to please
some
nasty god or projecting
the desire for parental approval on the
rest of the world or whatever like all
that
child consciousness nonsense and then
it's even wanting to like
respect myself and i have these values
and i want to be the kind of person i
respect okay that's fine those are steps
they all serve a role
but beyond that like when you read
roomie or you read hafez or you read
saint francis
they were just in love with the
beauty of the world
they just loved the birds and the trees
and the
every they they saw the beauty of it and
they were just in love with it
and the desire to serve that which
you're in love with is just a naturally
arising thing
that sounds awesome and this is now
in fact perfective and perception
is like when people do mushrooms when
they do psilocybin one of the really
interesting things is
you can do a big dose of mushrooms where
you're really tripping right and
you're
seeing colors that aren't there and
shapes whatever but when you're on a
smaller dose but you're clearly
altered one of the neat experiences
is you go outside and you look at a tree
and you start crying because it's so
beautiful and you sit there for an hour
just looking at the tree and you feel
like you could look at it for eternity
and never see the tree fully because
it's so intricate and amazing and
beautiful
and then at a certain point you ask
yourself
i've walked by this tree a million times
and never noticed it
why is it so much more beautiful now
you're like the tree's not purple it's
still the same color it still looks like
the same shape if i had to describe it
i would use the same why is it so much
more beautiful
oh i'm actually noticing it for the
first time
because i'm not so busy with this
emptiness
sense that is trying to go get full in
agendas and thinking about people and
laundry lists and whatever that i'm
actually just being present with and
it's just
actually that beautiful and there's this
neuroinhibitory function of certain
brain regions that involve narrative
that distracts us where there's
increased attention of consciousness in
the sensory processes where
if your senses if you really get to be
with your sentences which is again why
buddhist and taoist other techniques
talk about really dropping into the
senses
is because when you can have your
attention really with it the world's
beautiful
when you get that all violence the basis
for all the violence is gone
i think that's probably one of the best
ways to uh
to end this the world is
beautiful
yeah and arising from that sense of the
beauty is the desire to protect it
and to serve it and add to it the
artistic impulse
is the desire to add to it right a lot
of the humanitarian impulses the desire
to protect it and serve it but they all
arise out of seeing it
recognizing
awesome i i'm really happy we took we
took this turn in the end
and that you shared it daniel i really
truly appreciate
your investment of time and
sharing so many of your perspectives and
experiences and thoughts
um so yeah very very happy to have you
thank you this was really fun and
yeah we could have talked about more
things if if this ends up being
interesting to the people that you share
it with and we want to talk about more
things in the future we can
i'd love that um i will share some of my
favorite other pieces from you because
you
you should like you you create content
you are on other podcasts
um so that if someone is interested you
can follow
down in the rabbit hole as so have i and
there's more content
to catch up on and um also besides that
is there a specific channel or
way people can follow you or or reach
out to you in case there's
some interesting synergies
was as problematic and up a tool
as it is i actually do post stuff on
facebook sometimes
facebook is actually probably the best
place for stuff
i put up a blog a few years ago uh
civilizationemerging.com i don't add to
it very often but there's some old stuff
there
awesome okay again thanks for
for being on the pod and uh yeah we talk
soon
be well great being with you
you